<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Lean Living]]></title>
  <link href="http://pferdefleisch.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pferdefleisch.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-08T15:54:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://pferdefleisch.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aaron Cruz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2 Month Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://pferdefleisch.github.io/blog/blog/2014/05/06/2-month-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T11:43:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://pferdefleisch.github.io/blog/blog/2014/05/06/2-month-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I am a freelance software developer with a productivity problem. I work from home and sit in a chair all day so any exercise that I do needs effort and planning. I am slightly overweight according to the Body Mass Index Chart at 175cm(5&#8217; 10&#8221;) and 82.5 kg (182 lbs).</p>

<p><img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e9/Body_mass_index_chart.svg" alt="BMI chart" /><br/>
<em>image via wikipedia.com</em></p>

<h2>Lean Living</h2>

<p>I recently read a great book that really spoke to me called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1937785319/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=1937785319&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=blogaaroncruz-20&amp;linkId=VJADUBS27EJ44MPS">The Healthy Programmer</a>. In it Joe Kutner describes how you can iterate and make sprints on your diet and exercise like software developers do with agile development techniques. Instantly the gears in my brain started turning. I decided I wanted to take this idea and apply it to all parts of my life.</p>

<p>This also falls in line with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_Startup">Lean Startup</a> way of thinking. I will create small experiments, exercise plans, timeboxing for productivity. One thing I have learned over the years as a freelancer is that some of these techniques work great for some people some times. It&rsquo;s like a great book on programming. You really need to get the right book at the right point of understanding. A great book can be totally worthless if you aren&rsquo;t at the right point in your knowledge of the topic.</p>

<h2>Experiment, Measure, Iterate</h2>

<p>I have created productivity, diet, sleep and exercise goals that I wish to reach in 2 months time. I have also added a goal of building an releasing my own product. I wish to eventually move away from client work and working full time on my own projects.</p>

<h3>Daily stand ups</h3>

<p>I will do a daily &ldquo;stand up&rdquo; where I spend 5 minutes reviewing what where I&rsquo;m at, what I did well the day before and what I can do better today. I will contemplate these things during a 10 minute stretching session every morning.</p>

<h3>Weekly Review</h3>

<p>Every Sunday I will do a weekly review where I look at what went poorly and what went well and what I can change the next week. I will remove the bad and emphasize the good until the next Sunday where I repeat the process.</p>

<h2>Habits</h2>

<p>One of the main goals of this experiment is to create and nurture good habits. After you repeat something regularily enough, it often becomes a habit. I want to make going to bed at a reasonable time a habit. My current habit is staying up late and waking up early.</p>

<p>Using the sleep example, I need to consciously stop going to bed later than, say 11:00. After I get rid of that habit, I know from my past, it won&rsquo;t be something I have to think about anymore.</p>

<h2>Goals</h2>

<h3>Productivity</h3>

<p><strong>Billable Hours</strong><br/>
current: 15<br/>
goal: 30</p>

<h3>Diet</h3>

<p><strong>Weight</strong><br/>
current: 82.5kg<br/>
goal: 75kg<br/>
<strong>Body Fat</strong><br/>
current: 29%<br/>
goal: 20%</p>

<h3>Exercise</h3>

<p><strong>current</strong>
running: 4k<br/>
push ups: 20<br/>
pull ups: 0<br/>
<strong>goal</strong><br/>
running: 10k<br/>
push ups: 100<br/>
pull ups: 20</p>

<h3>Sleep</h3>

<p><strong>goal</strong>: at least 7.5 hours/night</p>

<h3>Product</h3>

<p>build an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">Minimum Viable Product</a> and release it</p>

<h2>The Talk</h2>

<p>I will be turning this all into a talk that I wish to give at some tech conferences around Europe and hopefully the world. If you have any questions, ask them in the comments or contact me via <a href="http://twitter.com/mraaroncruz">@mraaroncruz</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p>And if you have any tips, especially for productivity which is my weakest point, send them my way. I am really looking forward to the outcome of the experiment. I can&rsquo;t wait.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
